A Guide to the Papers of Francis James Child 1871-1893
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Francis James Child 1871-1893
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7545
13 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Forms part of the Clifton Waller Barrett Library.
Biographical/Historical Information
Author, philologist, scholar; known for his multivolume collection of English and Scottish Popular Ballads.
Scope and Content Information
13 items consisting of 12 pieces of correspondence and an engraving
Arrangement
The letters are arranged in two chronological sections. The first contains letters to personal correspondents. The second contains letters to his publisher.
Contents List
- Francis J. Child to Thomas R. Lounsbury, 1871 September 18, ALS, 4p.
  Child has received letter from Merriam's about Hadley's History of the English Navy. Humorously compares start of new school term with arrival of ships to the Hebrides. Is suffering from red cholera for which he has consulted Dr. Chaucer and is picking up all the cats fur and sailor berries he can find. Comments on making things plesant for enemies and unpleasant for friends. Best cathartic is a righteous quarrel with someone. Would he like Ben Butler for a purge? If there are no rascals in Connecticut he can supply him with a full line on short notice. Regards to all at Yale.
- Francis J. Child to Allen Thomas, Jr., 1880 February 10, ALS, 4p.
  Mentions Haverford and his friends in Baltimore. Enquires about a contribution to Transactions of the American Academy which was never in print. Hoped to do another one based on excellent texts now available. [A. J.] Ellis has included a part of it in Early English Pronunciation. Can't lend him the Chaucer paper but Ellis's book has the substance of it.
- Francis J. Child to Dr. Francis Minot Weld, 1882 February 16, ALS, 4p.
  Child regrets that his rheumatism and general debility prevent him from accepting an invitation to a Harvard dinner.
- Francis J. Child to H. H. Boyesen, 1882 April 1, ALS, 4p.
  Child writes about dying out of traditions in the Shetland Islands. Mentions an unnamed ballad that was noted 100 years ago. Speech there is so corrupted that [Norwegian philologist] Peter A. Munch could not understand it. Discusses a part of speech that has disappeared from all dialects. Would value Boyesen's opinion of some bits of Shetland rhyme in Munch's account.
- Francis J. Child to A[lmond?] W[hiting?] Griswold, 1887 November 3, ALS, 2p.
  Offers a Chaucer Society publication for examination. Publications have not been as successful as deserve to be.
- Francis J. Child to unnamed "Dear Professor," n.d., ALS, 3p.
  Answers a query by reference to the London Athenaeum article. No students in Anglo Saxon currently at Cambridge. Discusses merits of editions of Beowulf by Benjamin Thorpe and Moriz Heyne. Disparages the former who may be right in one or two places. Praises scholarship of John M. Kemble.
- Francis J. Child to [Almond Whiting?] Griswold, n.d., ALS, 4p.
  Concerns the Chaucer Society and the publication of Chaucer texts. No edition of Chaucer definitive without reference to the texts now being published. Will send a set. Recommends A.J. Ellis's book On early English pronunciation, with especial reference to Shakspere and Chaucer. Please recommend the Society to other New York book lovers.
- Francis J. Child to H. O. Houghton & Co., 1883 April 2, ASPC
  Corrected proof for pp. 89-96 [of English and Scottish Popular Ballads] did not come with the revision.
- Francis J. Child to H. O. Houghton & Co., 1884 May 17, ASPC
  Received proofs of [B____?] but there are revisions of earlier material he has not seen.
- Francis J. Child to H. O. Houghton & Co., 1886 June 28, ASPC
  His boy will bring revisions.
- Francis J. Child to H. O. Houghton & Co., 1887 December 3, ASPC
  Writes concerning the setting of Part IV and revisions to Part V of [ English and Scottish Popular Ballads].
- Francis J. Child to H. O. Houghton & Co., 1893 November 7, ASPC
  Wants a copy of number 266 in [ English and Scottish Popular Ballads] to send to Germany for possible additions.
- Portrait of Francis J. Child, n.d., Engraving; ca. 6 x 9in.
  Profile of the head of Child.